Finding Aid for Michigan Women's Assembly Records, 1982-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Women's Assembly Records, 1982-1991
Michigan Women's Assembly
1 linear ft.
0543 Bk 2
The Michigan Women's Assembly (MWA) was the largest coalition of women's organizations in the state in the 1980's. The purpose of the MWA was to establish and implement a Platform designed to promote equal status for women in society. To qualify for membership the organization had to support the Equal Rights Amendment and "to not oppose the right of every women to secure an abortion." The records reflect MWA's organizational activity from 1982 to 1991.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from Alicia Perez-Banuet (donor no. 8608 ) in December 2004.
The record group is open to research.
The Michigan Women's Assembly by-laws date from June, 1985 but the first Organizing Committee meeting was held in 1982. The issue-focus of the organization drove the activities which were based on the implementation of the Platform. The Platform was a comprehensive statement of the concerns of Michigan women and was drafted and ratified biennially in June in even numbered years, utilizing a prioritizing mechanism. The Platform was intended to serve as a women's movement agenda. Each Platform Convention addressed six issues: Power and Image, Education, Employment and the Economy, Family Relations and Health Care, Community Concerns, and International Relations.
Through discussion and consensus, resolutions within each issue were arrived at and then distilled in a candidate survey which was given to political candidates in August and September. The survey results were tabulated in October. Then strategies for implementing the Platform were distributed to the media, candidates, political parties, and the member women's organizations. Attaining the goals of the Platform was monitored by the MWA Board of Directors at quarterly meetings.
The record group is divided into four series: Administration, 1982-1990, Biennial Business Convention, 1987-1991, Legislative Activities, 1987-1990, and Platform, 1982-1990.
Subjects:
Michigan Women's Assembly.; Equal rights amendments--United States.; Women's rights--Michigan.
- Administration, 1982-1990
  Administration, 1982-1990, series contains by-laws, correspondence, budgets, membership information, minutes, and reports.
  - Background information (Box 1)
  - By-Laws (Box 1)
  - Notebooks
    - 1985-1987
      - Members (Box 1)
      - Minutes (Box 1)
      - Retreat (Box 1)
    - 1987-1988
      - Correspondence (Box 1)
      - Members (Box 1)
      - Minutes (Box 1)
    - 1988-1990
      - Correspondence (Box 1)
      - Members (Box 1)
      - Minutes (Box 1)
      - Reports (Box 1)
  - Organizing Committee, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
- Biennial Business Convention, 1987-1991
  Biennial Business Convention, 1987-1991 series contains records relating to the meeting in June of odd-numbered years held for the purpose of electing officers, amending by-laws and attending to other business.
  - 1987 (Box 1)
  - 1989 (Box 1)
  - 1991 (Box 1)
- Legislative Activities, 1987-1990
  Legislative Activities, 1987-1990, series contains records of the Legislative Committee and related organizational and informational documents.
  - Legislative Committee
    - 1987 (Box 1)
    - 1989, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Legislative Issues
    - 1983 (Box 1)
    - 1985 (Box 1)
  - Legislative Notebook, 1989-1990, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Platform, 1982-1990
  The Platform, 1982-1990, series contains copies of the Platform statement and other documentation related to the drafting of the Platform for various years.
  - 1982 (Box 1)
  - 1984 (Box 1)
  - 1986, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - 1988 (Box 1)
  - 1990 (Box 1)